Guide to the Voices of Brooklyn oral histories 2008.031
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Brooklyn oral histories: Our neighbors, 2007-; 2008.031.5
  - Moran, Ed, 2008 November 12; 2008.031.5.016
    Abolitionists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Amateur theater |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z New York |x Clergy; Presbyterians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religious institutions |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; Slavery |z United States |x History; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Moran, Ed, 2008 November 26; 2008.031.5.017
    Edward "Ed" Moran was born in 1947 and raised in a small town of Pennsylvania. At age twenty in 1968, he sailed to Europe for a four-month tour of the continent. Moving to New York City later that year, he lived in Manhattan until 1974. After moving to Brooklyn, he joined a theatrical company that performed at Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church. In 1976, he formally became a member of the church. He became an Elder with the Session of the church a year later and, after less involvement in the church for much of the 1980s, he joined the Session again from 1989 to 1991. Writing for a living, Moran is recognized as the unofficial historian of Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church; knowledgeable about the church's mid-nineteenth century origin and subsequent decades, and equipped with first-hand observations of the 1970s through the 2000s.
    In this second of three interviews, Edward "Ed" Moran begins with his recollections of Reverend George Knight and the creativity and sense of community that Moran enjoyed at Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church. He looks at the the social justice mission of the church through the lens of the More Light Presbyterians coalition that began at the church in 1979 with little difficulty. He examines how More Light was reaffirmed in the early 1990s with some challenges by those affected by a Religious Right ideology. Moran cites this same period as a time of upheaval in the church's functionality because of the Reverend Knight's personal troubles, his swift resignation, and an ensuing chaotic three-year period of four interim pastors. The details of that period were expected to be part of the follow-up oral history. While recording, Moran requested that some thoughts on Rev. Fred Davie be redacted. Two minutes late in the first hour have been cut. Interview conducted by Hillel Arnold.
    Amateur theater |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Church controversies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Church management |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gay rights; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Clergy; Presbyterians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religious institutions |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Moran, Ed, 2009 January 29; 2008.031.5.018
    In this third of three interviews, Edward "Ed" Moran delves into the challenges of a three-and-a-half year period between permanent pastors at Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church in 1989 to 1992. He goes into detail about some of the interim pastors, Reverend Davie's role as associate pastor, and the institutional chaos in the wake of Reverend George Knight's tumultuous final days as pastor. He describes the procedures of the Session and their role in reaffirming the More Light position of the church; an open-door policy to welcome members to be of any sexual preference, as well as electing Reverend David Dyson as permanent pastor. Both efforts were challenged by a few members and by the lingering disarray of Rev. Knight's management. Moran looks at this period as a reflection of larger movements happening in 1990s America. He hypothesizes about the church's future and church attendance in general, then breaks down what appeals to him and others about attending services. Moran closes with visceral memories of old Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church sights and sounds. While recording, Moran expressed that he was making a personal aside that was not for the record. One minute near the one hour mark was cut. Interview conducted by Hillel Arnold.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Church controversies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Church management |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gay rights; Identity politics; Politics and culture |z United States; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Clergy; Sexuality & culture; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Santos, Frank, 2008 September 5; 2008.031.5.019
    One of six children, Frank Santos was born in 1927 and raised on Hicks Street in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood. His parents had emigrated from the Canary Islands in the early 1920s. He and several siblings followed their father into the woodworking trades. As a child, Santos attended the parochial Assumption School in the Heights. A father and grandfather, he was also a Florida resident as of 2017.
    In the interview, Frank Santos shares many of his and his family's biographical details. He tells of the disruption to the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood caused by the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway, as well as his family's relocation to a new Hicks Street home. Santos vividly recalls many features of 1930s and 1940s Downtown Brooklyn and Heights neighborhoods. He speaks of his schooling at the Assumption School, and then quickly moves into an overview of the careers of his children and grandchildren. Focusing on one daughter's challenges in a couple marriages to police officers, Santos expresses his criticism of the police in general and the New York Police Department specifically; citing encounters he experienced in 1959, the 1970s, and 2007. The interview ends abruptly due to an issue with the recording equipment. Santos was interviewed again, weeks later, and that interview is also within this series. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn-Queens Expressway (New York, N.Y.); Catholic schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community gardens |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Elections |x Corrupt practices |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Florida; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; School children--New York (State)--Kings County; Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bergen Cabinet (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Esposito, Diana; Santos, Frank
  - Santos, Frank with Gaffney, Elizabeth, 2008 October 27; 2008.031.5.020
    One of six children, Frank Santos was born in 1927 and raised on Hicks Street in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. His parents had emigrated from the Canary Islands in the early 1920s. He and several siblings followed their father into the woodworking trades. As a child, Santos attended the parochial Assumption School in the Heights. A father and grandfather, he was also a Florida resident as of 2017.
    As stated on her website, Elizabeth Gaffney is also "a native Brooklynite. She graduated with honors from Vassar College and holds a master's degree in fiction from Brooklyn College; she also studied philosophy and German at Ludwig-Maximillian University in Munich. She lives in Brooklyn with her husband, the neurologist Alex Boro, and their daughters. Her second novel, When the World Was Young, was published by Random House in 2014." The story is set in Brooklyn Heights in the period of the Second World War.*
    *Source: http://www.elizabethgaffney.net/author.html
    In the interview, Frank Santos begins with some of his family's biographical details, then describes local doctors in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of his youth. He recalls many elements of his childhood throughout the interview; such as building wagons and scooters to race with friends, the neighborhood before the disruption of the Brooklyn Queens Expressway, and personal hygiene in a cold water flat. Santos vividly recalls amenities and features of the 1930s and 1940s Downtown Brooklyn and Brooklyn Heights neighborhoods. He speaks of his respect for Jewish neighbors and their philanthropy. Aspects of life during World War II like working on oil barges for the Army, rationing, blackouts, air raid warnings, and soldiers on duty in Cadman Plaza. Elizabeth Gaffney shares a few details about her history with the Heights and she and Santos make comparisons about real estate and investment in the area. Prior to this oral history, Santos was interviewed weeks earlier, and that interview is also within this series. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan, with Elizabeth Gaffney contributing interview questions as part of her writing preparation.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn-Queens Expressway (New York, N.Y.); Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; School children--New York (State)--Kings County; Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945 |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gaffney, Elizabeth; Santos, Frank; United States. Army
  - Vadheim, Robert, 2008 November 6; 2008.031.5.022
    Dr. Robert Vadheim (1919-2010), a physician, was a longtime resident of Brooklyn. Dr. Vadheim and his partner Robert Johnson moved to the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1964. During the 1960s, he became an active member of the community, promoting historic preservation and the revitalization of the borough's neighborhoods. Vadheim also volunteered and made philanthropic contributions to local institutions. His donations led to significant preservation projects in the Heights, such as the restoration of stained glass windows at the Church of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity, and the installation of a working timepiece on the clock tower of Brooklyn Historical Society's building. In 2005, Vadheim received the Brooklyn Heights Association's Award for Extraordinary Community Service. His donations to the Brooklyn Historical Society include works of art and manuscript collections that document changes in Brooklyn and its surroundings during the mid to late 20th century.*
    *Source Surratt, Jerl. "Dr. Robert Vadheim, Enthusiast of Heights Preservation, Dies at 90." Brooklyn Daily Eagle, August 11, 2010. http://www.brooklyneagle.com/categories/category.php?category_id=24&id=37348
    In the interview, Dr. Robert Vadheim touches on the instrumental people involved in a few notable architectural preservation projects. He briefly describes his office view and commute when he practiced at 30 Rockefeller Plaza. Dr. Vadheim then reads a letter from Brendan Gill, circa 1982. He discusses his role as a trustee and his familiarity with Brooklyn Historical Society. Dr. Vadheim recalls some biographical details of his Minnesota origin and youth, including his printmaking hobby and his arrival in New York in 1939. He discusses a potential donation of World Trade Center-related news clippings and recalls both terrorist incidents there. Dr. Vadheim then brings his guests on a tour of his Willow Street home. Due to a recording issue, very little of the narrator can be heard after the first half hour. Three blocks of time totaling sixty-two minutes were removed due to inaudible content in the latter eighty minutes of the recording. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan, with Janice Monger and Deborah Schwartz.
    Architecture |x Conservation and restoration; Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Intellectual life; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Brownstone buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic preservation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Minnesota; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Popular music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.); Gill, Brendan, 1914-1997; Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.); Vadheim, Robert
  - Vanasco, Rocco "Roy", 2013 August 08; 2008.031.5.023
    Rocco Vanasco, who went by Roy most of his life, was born in 1926 to an Italian American family. He and four brothers were raised in a few different homes within the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended PS 12, PS 67, and Manual Training High School, enlisting in the Navy prior to graduation. Vanasco served on the destroyer, U.S.S. Osterhaus, in the Pacific Theater during World War II. Returning to civilian life, he briefly repaired appliances for General Electric and at his home. After buying a building with a storefront in the late 1950s, he and his brother Jack opened up a repair shop there in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn. With Abe Stark as his role model, Rocco Vanasco threw himself into community service; forming or joining local civic entities like the Rockefeller Republican Club, Community Board Two, the Eighty-Eighth Precinct Community Council, and the Myrtle Avenue Merchants' Association. He resided in New Jersey at the time of the 2013 interviews. The brothers closed their shop in early 2017, to make way for a new apartment building on the same lot.
    In the first of two interviews, Rocco Vanasco begins with his family's Italian immigrant heritage and how his parents met and married. He describes the living quarters of his aunt's house at 178 Clermont Avenue in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn, where his parents and three brothers closely occupied one floor. He recalls street play with friends and economic hardship for his family during the Great Depression. Vanasco recalls his public schooling, then transitions to his community work and involvement in the local politics of Fort Greene. At different points, he describes Myrtle Avenue in the contexts of his efforts to establish a drug rehabilitation facility, attracting city services to keep the street orderly and clean, and recollecting scenery and storefronts of the Avenue's past. Vanasco describes his service in the Navy during the final months of war in the Pacific and the trip back to the States; including his ship docking in the Brooklyn Navy Yard late in 1945. He also shares episodes of his chairing different committees and other instances of civic improvements. Interview conducted by Rebecca Jacobs.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Docks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Games |x Street |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhood government |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Vinegar Hill (New York, N.Y.); World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States. Navy; Vanasco, Rocco
  - Vanasco, Rocco "Roy", 2013 August 20; 2008.031.5.024
    In the second of two interviews, Rocco Vanasco begins with his studies in electrical work and how he established a refrigerator repair shop. He mentions forming Community Board Two and describes his involvement in the local politics of the Clinton Hill and Fort Greene neighborhoods of Brooklyn. He recalls efforts to preserve landmarks of Fort Greene and how local government becomes focused on traffic issues. After a half hour, the interview is advanced by Vanasco's photos and the memories sparked by them: World War II, his public schooling, his family, establishing a drug rehabilitation storefront, witnessing looting during a blackout, working with other community organizers and organizations, and recalling the scenery and storefronts of the area's past, as well as how they were updated. Vanasco describes instances of civic activity like keeping excavated boulders in Fort Greene Park and keeping a firehouse open. In closing, he recalls painting homes with his father and how the family got along on a low income. Interview conducted by Rebecca Jacobs.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Games |x Street |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Neighborhood government |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Vinegar Hill (New York, N.Y.); World War, 1939-1945 |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community Board No. 2 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Manual Training High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Myrtle Avenue Merchants Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York Naval Shipyard; Stark, Abe; Vanasco, Rocco
  - Williams, Fenton, 2013 August 9; 2008.031.5.027
    Fenton Williams was born in Suffolk, Virginia in 1931 and raised in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended the area's public elementary schools and a Manhattan vocational high school. Shortly after beginning in the city's community college and passing a test for a coveted position within the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Williams was drafted into the Army during the Korean War. After his service, he returned to school and to a job in the Yard as a shipwright. He married and raised a family in a house bought in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1958. After the close of the Yard, Williams went to work for the city as a building inspector and carpenter in the late 1960s. He then became a plant mechanic at Greenpoint Hospital, and followed that with higher superintendent and foreman positions at Cumberland and Woodhull Hospitals. Williams and his wife moved to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1984. He was a grandfather and widower by 2013.
    In the interview, Fenton Williams tells the broad history of his family origins; a legacy that included slavery and former slaves and field hands in the South. He describes his many siblings; several of whom were lost to tuberculosis, and life in Brooklyn's cold water flats. Williams shares vivid details about childhood play in the Fort Greene neighborhood and surrounding areas of Brooklyn. He recalls the interaction between African American and Italian American people in Fort Greene; it was largely neighborly in the 1930s and 1940s, but racially-motivated fighting did occur. Williams outlines his education from public elementary schools to a technical high school to community college. The middle of the interview is largely about his work as a shipwright in the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Williams runs through his many jobs after the Yard closed and goes into detail on his wife's dress-making and careers of their three children. He ends with a description of home ownership in the Park Slope and Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhoods, from the 1950s to 1980s. Interview conducted by Rebecca Jacobs.
    African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Voices of Brooklyn oral histories: Sports and leisure, 2008-; 2008.031.6
  This series includes oral histories collected through several projects undertaken by Brooklyn Historical Society beginning in 2008. The assembled collection took shape in 2008 under the project title "Brooklyn History Makers." The ongoing oral history collection, retitled in 2016, features a range of narrators: Amateur athletes, sports players, and Coney Island performers recall personal moments and the changes they have observed in their neighborhoods over decades.
  - Arrocha, Edward, 2009 April 29; 2008.031.6.001
  - King, Albert, 2009 November 4; 2008.031.6.002
    Albert King was born in 1959 and raised along with four brothers and one sister on Myrtle Avenue in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. Attending public school, he began playing basketball at age ten. He played on the teams at Sands Junior High School and Fort Hamilton High School in Brooklyn. Attaining a basketball scholarship, King played for the University of Maryland Terrapins beginning in 1977. Drafted by the New Jersey Nets in 1981, he played professional ball for nine seasons, until 1991. Within a few years, he was looking into running a Wendy's restaurant and was a co-investor in one in 1995. In 1998, he became a sole Wendy's franchisee, expanding to ownership of three restaurants. As recently as 2015, King was giving tips to kids playing ball in NBA (National Basketball Association) Cares clinics.